[Music]
hello everyone this is Frank defreitis
and welcome to holotalk the internet's
laser and holography talk show enjoyed
in over 42 countries throughout the
world and now here's this week's show
[Music]
hello John how are you it's Frank de
Freitas
good to hear your voice too
how would you like to start off I mean
when I visit your site I've known of
your site for a long time now I I find
it an amazing resource not only for the
work that you've done over the years in
holography but also for some of the
Priceless photos that you have on there
as well
historically speaking oh good well I'm
glad you like that yeah I've been very
fortunate to uh to have been a witness
to some of this I think would be the way
to characterize it when you were growing
up you lived in Oak Ridge right correct
what was your connection with Oak Ridge
in those days was that just a town or
were you with a military family or
something
no uh Oak Ridge was you know created
during World War II as part of the
Manhattan Project
a lot of young people
um converged on the town from all over
the United States because they had
either special skills or because they
were local folks that that needed work
and um
as a result uh well well John fairstein
was one of the results of that
collaboration of peace and
after the war
in addition to the Manhattan Project
facilities uh the Oak Ridge National
Laboratory had been created and uh there
was a tremendous amount of research
going on there and continues to this
it's one of the Premier Laboratories in
the in the world that's where you saw
your first laser demonstration was at
the Oak Ridge National Laboratory and
and that was just that that was a real
Epiphany for me I think I was like uh 11
or 12 years old and my father took me
down to the high school auditorium where
um
this was in like 1963 or 64 shortly
after the first helium neon laser had
been demonstrated yeah you don't happen
to remember the early manufacturers was
a division of Hughes aircraft that was
making the first teeny lasers in
production do you know
yeah I remember those too yeah
and some of those folks
folks early start and one of the
companies at a very early starter was uh
called PSR
Incorporated here no cribs and they made
lasers for
sir and this was the same group of guys
uh Percy stats Henry Morgan Mila
Skidmore and George Werner uh among
other ones who put on this demonstration
at the high school okay and it was
astounding I mean no we had never seen
laser light and they had they had it
bouncing all around the auditorium they
were at that time they were even
transmitting South off of the laser beam
wow and you know this was a laser that
they had made they they had their own
glass blowing shop oh okay
uh their own facilities and these guys
just they when they read the original
papers they were all over it and
immediately again building their own
lasers and and of course they wanted to
demonstrate it to the community so it
was just astounding I mean and for me a
little kid you know to see this was was
uh I never forgot it I can I can clearly
remember to this day sitting there and
looking at that beam and the speckle
pattern mm-hmm
and you know I continued I've known
those guys ever since uh
um so and in fact an interesting little
Sideline Story
is that uh when Dr XI from the now
famous Lake Forest College
was actually
employed at ORNL shortly after that
some reason all of this paperwork hadn't
been completed yet so he was kind of
twiddling his thumbs and these guys said
well listen you know you might want to
play around with this thing uh these
lasers and this new thing calligraphy so
uh Dr Zion spent spent a year at ORNL
with sort of free access to some big
Granite tables and lasers and and that's
where his holography career got started
it was right here in Oak Ridge no
kidding
now that is an interesting Side Story
and uh and to this day I think one of
those guys that had demonstrated that
laser to me Henry Morgan uh he and uh
and Dr Zion are still I'm assuming
they're still in Communications yeah I
haven't talked to Henry in a long time
but let me ask you this do you happen to
remember during the demonstration
what applications they mentioned
the laser was used for presently and
future applications well they they you
know it's been a long long time 1963.
sure time ago but uh I I distinctly
remember them transmitting sound
[Music]
amazing to everyone and I think they
also discussed the idea of uh of
transmitting you know not only sound but
data and you know and other information
it
time I don't think holography had been
uh what had been popularized so I don't
think that that was part of the
discussion but uh certainly transmitting
data and sound was yeah it must it must
have been very close to
um or very shortly after
Emmett Leaf at the University of
Michigan with the first laser
transmission hologram up there
correct yeah so after that what did you
do did you still continue to have an
interest in lasers and that's what
eventually LED you out to San Francisco
in the 70s well I
I ended the college in Ohio
a couple of my classmates were a
lawnmower and Randy James who have later
achieved a prominence in holography oh
yeah and we uh we uh all three of us
went to San Francisco where our College
had started a branch program out there
under the auspices of the University
Without Walls which
great idea of the idea being that the
university would just have an office and
that we would our classroom would be the
entire community
so uh
they were actually just starting that in
Philadelphia when I was in high school
with high school Without Walls as well
oh yeah okay well I thought that was a
great idea and so I jumped on that
opportunity
in Randy James
also came out there and uh in the course
of our our studies a lot was introduced
to Lloyd cross and the Lord came to the
college and
frustration of holograms and what he did
was he had these big uh I guess they
were about one foot diameter cardboard
tubes that were maybe three or four feet
high
put the laser down in the bottom a
little one milliwatt laser and then and
put a lens on it and then put the
hologram on top of the tube so it made a
very nice little
display
and these Holograms were just terrific
they were four by fives and eight by ten
transmission hole exams that were
illuminated by this laser down in the
base of the tube and then
Crystal Clear they were they were
completely Noise free just just you
beautiful homes laser transmission
Holograms are beautiful Holograms yeah
and they had tremendous course
tremendous depth and you know and and
it's uh it's exactly like uh in in your
interview with my good friend Steve
Province where he
you have this small Epiphany when you
see this and and that's exactly true you
see it in in your your pupils contract
and your whole body becomes
resounded by what you see and even today
when I see a whole band this has a
simpler effect well I was just
been uh in a meeting
signed up with the school of Photography
to take the basic callography class
and there I meant uh of course I already
knew lawn and I met Fred under share and
uh Gary Adams and Lloyd cross and
Michael Khan and all of the
denizens of the School of photography
biography and was introduced Lloyd
conducted a lecture in the back of the
school of holography that
described some of the political
principles behind the whole thing and
then Lon or Gary or or whoever would
come out and give us some instruction in
in the basic techniques of sandbox a lot
and what they had done is they had built
uh sort of a four by eight foot box out
of uh cinder blocks and filled it full
of sand and this was
the idea that Jerry Pathak had had
introduced and then we mounted all the
Optics on the ends of PVC pipe and
sand and arranged it and then after you
had everything arranged you let it
settle for 30 minutes or so and then
shot your hologram well
you can't imagine something more
exciting than that especially in 1973
you know when you see your first
hologram it's just I mean you know they
were very primitive you know what I was
doing but gosh it was so exciting and uh
you know and then and then they you know
things that begin to develop out of
there you know they begin to experiment
with uh I remember Steve Benton came and
showed a uh a rainbow hologram well
immediately there
school started scrambling around
scratching their head trying to figure
out well how did he do that and uh
within within three days Lloyd had had
completely
the whole process out and and we were
shooting rainbow Holograms down there
and uh then it was just a couple of
steps away to the multiplex Holograms
and uh you know I was kind of I kind of
uh
say I was an active participant I sort
of lurked in the whole thing but uh I
got to witness a little bit of the the
first camera the First multiplex camera
and then some subsequent developments in
that so just fascinating certainly
nothing wrong with just being a witness
to all that happening for the most part
it's this I would compare that to
someone saying well all I did was just
sit on the floor while the Beatles were
recording
an address keeps popping up into my mind
tonight maybe you can resolve this
address for me what does Shotwell Street
mean to you well that's where the school
is that where that was okay
I think it was 454 Shotwell Street or
something like that okay
you know it was this enormous uh
Warehouse that was kind of divided into
two halves and on one half was was the
holographic Studio and there was uh oh I
don't know three or four of these uh
sandbox setups that allowed them to
teach plan
and then they had an experimental uh a
little dedicated what they called a
holographic camera that was used to make
a reflection Holograms
there's another little area where they
were building up the multiplexer and
then on the other side uh the folks that
that were active
um like Gary Adams and uh Pam and and
Lloyd and Michael and all those folks
lived on the other side that kind of had
little Loft areas where they where they
lived Pam is the woman that eventually
wound up in Lloyd cross's kiss right
yeah yeah exactly Pam Brazier and uh and
there was just any number of people that
floated through this
this Warehouse you know what what type
of people were they were they artists
were they scientists were kind of a
combination yeah
uh there were some of them were very
technical uh I remember there was a guy
there that worked directly with Lloyd in
in the Lloyd had created this method of
stretching a membrane off of across a
speaker and then attaching a small
mirror to it and produces light shows I
remember that well this guy I don't
remember his name but he was kind of a
uh you know what what we would call
nowadays a geek you know he was sort of
a very technical person and very able to
concentrate uh you know his energies on
this particular problem and then there
were other people
Pam and other folks that were more
artistic and uh you know had very
creative ideas about how how
hologography could be applied to
the visual arts and and just uh just a
home mix of different folks in there
that uh all of them just brilliant and
energetic and uh you know it was it was
a fantastic environment
oh that's incredible I thought I'd also
like to point out some
this whole
you know from my point of view from what
I've seen holography
is as much a a a social a kind of a
social Dynamic uh as it was a scientific
or engineering or artistic uh media
because it attracted so many uh diverse
people with different ideas and uh you
know kind of a very free thinking at
that time and and
you got to remember that the political
landscape at that time was we were in
the midst of the Vietnam War when it
entered into uh into a deep recession
and uh there was I mean there were just
tremendous political forces
swirling around this Cavern called the
the school of holography so you know it
was it was quite a quite a scene you
eventually started your own company out
there as well right yes we did uh uh
lawnmower and Randy James and Fred
Hunter share and I uh and uh Nancy
corglioni and her friend Dave
um we started
in our friend Constance
uh started what we called Celestial hold
rims which was based out of a house
Richmond
did San Francisco
and we found a house that was sort of
isolated from a lot of traffic and had a
big basement in it and uh we built an
enormous five five foot by 10 by 10 foot
uh sandbox
had on a huge concrete slab and I think
the idea there was that we wanted to
have long
throws for our beams so that we could uh
produce some eight some good quality
eight by ten Masters without having to
uh Optics
and uh Michael Khan uh my my dear friend
Michael Khan built us a laser in in
typical mic confession it was a Bare
Bones laser that you know all the power
supply was completely exposed and uh to
you know the high voltage was just right
there and in a long long tube with a
manually adjusted uh mirrors on it that
tweak those mirrors to get get it into
single mode operation but we uh we
started immediately producing some
Holograms and we take them down to the
Waterfront and sell them on the street
and uh oh that was so exciting because
people you know tourists would come and
they'd see that and they'd never seen
anything like that and and we'd go out
on a sunny day we didn't
they would just use sunlight and it the
the
reaction of people that came to see
these simple Holograms was fabulous I
mean they were delighted
oh you know something John I bet you
would have the same reaction today
I bet you would I believe we would it
it's just it's
it's like state
possible and you see
you have a small epiphany
and uh you know it's it's almost a small
orgasm the visual orgasm when you see
these things
so we uh we checked away and produced
Holograms and tried all different kinds
of things and you know we were under a
lot of all of us were under a lot of
personal financial pressures and we were
all very creative and independent-minded
people So eventually the the thing uh
you know kind of we we kind of separated
but uh uh you know the spirit kept going
I think Fred went went on and uh wrote
his famous book and went on and did just
some tremendous uh things and of course
lawn started a whole business and and
was very successful at that and Randy uh
later worked with Steve McGrew and then
took over that whole uh
operation of holographic mastering and I
think he continues with his Pacific
holographics I'm not sure of the name
but yeah I was just out on his website
the other night
Nancy uh corglioli of course went on it
did uh did some tremendous work and
collaborated with Michael Connell and
some vacuum deposition stuff
and I'm not sure what happened to her
friend Dave
but how everyone went on and continued
on and was successful in the in their
various fears of holography so
uh that was a very seminal little
company that's that's cholesterol
Holograms where did people Envision this
all leading did you think 10 years 20
years well what was the General thought
as to where all this was going and where
it would lead
well I'm
I was sort of in the moment and uh I
didn't have the uh the ability to think
very far out
but the the initial
excitement
um that from from the very first moment
that I saw Lloyd's Holograms at there at
Antioch West just propelled me along for
about
her 20 years
um I think uh some of the other folks I
think Fred and Lon and Randy had a
longer range Vision about what where
they fit in uh into holography and what
they wanted to do with it and uh you
know I think that they each did their
own personal way uh we're able to
achieve their goals
um I sort of was blowing in the Wind for
about 15 or 20 years
well I certainly can appreciate your
outlook of living in the moment because
I I strongly believe in that myself so
we're we're two birds of a feather when
it comes to that even today every day
as long as you take care of today
tomorrow usually takes care of itself
with that in mind what we're going to do
is let's take a quick break
because what I'd like to do is put this
into two parts because we're coming up
onto Close to 25 minutes and I like to
keep the file sizes manageable because
we do have a lot of listeners that are
overseas on dial-up connections and I
try to keep the file sizes small so
let's take a quick break and we'll come
back and for those of you who are
listening to it this week next week
we'll have part two